בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Today's דף *daf* is ל"א *Lamed Aleph*. First
of all, חודש טוב *Chodesh tov*. Today's דף *daf* is דף ל"א
*daf Lamed Aleph*. We start from the top,
and we are back sort of to the somewhat theme of this
פרק *perek*, which is getting food out of storage or from, you
know, from places in which it's been set aside. So there's obviously
a very dominant מוקצה muktzeh. *muktzah* theme again to this פרק
*perek*. Somewhat like the first one. 31, ל"א *Lamed Aleph*. מביאים עצים
מן השדה *Mevim etzim min hasadeh*, you can bring wood that is
from the field, מן המכונס *min hamichunas*. So if you have gathered
piles of wood in the field, and obviously that you're planning on
bringing back to your house and using for firewood, then you can
do it because then it's not מוקצה muktzeh *muktzah*. It's been piled
up and obviously you're planning on using it for firewood or for
some similar type of a use. ומן הקרפף *Umin hakarfaf*, and from
the yard. א קרפף karpef. *A karfaf* is not something that's like
way out in the field. As we'll see, it's closer to the
city. It's surrounded by a fence.
So that's what a קרפף karpef, *karfaf* is. It's something that's more
considered to be like a type of, you know, not just where
you go to harvest your grain, but you know, a yard makes
it sound like your front yard. I'm trying to think of a
good analogy. You know, it's more sort of like yes.
Didn't we see this in שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*?
Well, we definitely had קרפף karpef *karfaf*. קרפף karpef. *Karfaf* was a
big thing about הוקף לדירה *hukaf ledira*, לא הוקף לדירה *lo hukaf
ledira*. So it's some type of fenced-in area that is more, you
know, regularly used and therefore more accessible. So if you're bringing it
from the קרפף karpef *karfaf*, אפילו מן המפוזר *afilu min hamifuzar*, even
if the sticks are scattered and not in a pile, the fact
that they're in this קרפף karpef, *karfaf*, you know, clearly means that
they're things that you would expect to be using and therefore are
not considered מוקצה muktzeh? *muktzah*. איזהו קרפף eizehu karpef? *Eizu karfaf*, what
is considered a קרפף karpef. *karfaf*? כל שסמוך לעיר *Kol shesamuch le'ir*,
דברי רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *divrei Rabbi Yehuda*. Anything near the city,
so it sounds like that's the only difference. Near the city as
opposed to far away. How near is not exactly clear. That's what
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. אומר
*Rabbi Yosi omer*, no, there's another distinguishing factor of a קרפף karpef
*karfaf*. כל שנכנסין לו בפותחת *Kol shenichnasin lo bepotachat*, anything that you
go into with like a key, like a lock and a key,
it's fenced in. And then that makes it considered, you know, obviously
the more something is fenced in, the more it's sort of like,
you know, your home. And I mean maybe that's a little bit
taking it to an extreme, but something more under your control and
in this immediate sense of use. And therefore if it has that
aspect that it's fenced in and it's locked, אפילו בתוך תחום שבת
afilu betoch techum Shabbat, *afilu betoch techum Shabbat*, even if it's inside
the תחום שבת techum Shabbat, *techum Shabbat*. Now it doesn't mean way
in, it means it's even at the edge of the תחום *techum*
of שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. The תחום *techum* of שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat* is
relevant for יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* as well. And even
if it's at the very end of 2000 אמות *amot*, so it's
not close to the city, it's as far away as possible as
you could get to it on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*.
Nevertheless, if it is a קרפף karpef. *karfaf* that is fenced in,
then the stuff in there is not considered מוקצה muktzeh. *muktzah*. The
stuff in there is considered presumably
that you would want to have ready access to it and use
to it and therefore it is not מוקצה muktzah *muktzah*. So the
whole debate here is when is a stick מוקצה muktzah *muktzah* or
not based on are they scattered or piled up and where are
they located in a field or in this קרפף karpef. *karfaf*, and
what's important about the קרפף karpef. *karfaf*, the proximity or the fact
that it's fenced in. Now it's very important to note one issue
that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* raises, which is I don't get why the
only issue here is מוקצה muktzah *muktzah*. If you have sticks that
are scattered and you're gathering them up in a pile, isn't that
a
מלאכה melacha *melachah*? That's right, עימור *imur*. Exactly, according to some that
is one of the few מלאכות melachot *melachot* in the Torah, מקושש
עצים *mekoshish etzim*. If that's what the, you know, that's a reasonable
explanation of what the מקושש עצים *mekoshish etzim* was. Exactly, and at
עצים *etzim*. So let's take a look at תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot*. So
that's the question, might be the person who gathered up sticks. So
מן הקרפף אפילו מן המפוזר *min hakarfaf afilu min hamifuzar*, תימה *teimah*
says תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, הא הוי מעמר Me'amer? *ha havei me'amer*. This
is making, putting stuff in a
pile, gathering food in a pile, do אב מלאכה melacha. *av melachah*
which is an אב *av*, it's דאורייתא de'oraita *de'oraita*. ויש לומר דלא
שייך עימור אלא במקום שגידולן שם *Veyesh lomar d'lo shayach imur ela
bemakom shegidulan sham*. עימור *Imur* is the fruit fall off of a
tree or you harvest your wheat and it's lying in the field
after it's been cut and then you're going to gather it up
into bundles. עימור *Imur* is part of the process of taking stuff
from where it
grows and bringing it in and processing. So the apples fell off
the tree or the wheat was harvested and now you're going to
pull it all into a pile. If for example I spill my
pasta on the kitchen floor and I pick it all up, that's
not עימור *imur*. עימור
*Imur* is the raw food where it fell and gathering it. So
the sticks, but you would say oh that might be the case
of the sticks, the sticks in the קרפף karpef. *karfaf*. But apparently
not. Apparently maybe in the field scattered sticks if they fell off
of a tree could be עימור *imur*, but in the קרפף karpef
*karfaf* which is more like you know, I'm thinking of a קרפף
karpef *karfaf* it's more sort of like a baseball field, right? It's
not like a field out there where you have your wheat and
you're growing stuff. It's a yard like it's a park but anyway.
A lot. Something, yeah, that's the word I was looking for, it's
like a lot. So if there's scattered sticks there, it is not
because they just fell off the tree and this is part of
harvesting the sticks. Okay, but so that's important to note that תוספות
Tosafos is acknowledging there could be a דאורייתא de'oraita problem based on
the scenario.
I think it's usually vocalized as קרפף.
karpef? קרפף, karpef. okay, you could very well be correct. All right,
my mistake. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: אין מביאים עצים אלא
מן המכונסים שבקרפף. ein mevi'im etzim ela min hamukhunasin shebe-karpef. So he
says as opposed to the משנה Mishnah that says that if it's
in the קרפף karpef. it could be even scattered, he says and
the משנה Mishnah says one of two criteria: either gathered up or
in the קרפף אפילו מפוזרין. karpef afilu mefuzarin. He says רב יהודה
אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel that you need both criteria to
make it considered מוכן: mukhan: gathered and in the קרפף. karpef So
גמרא Gemara says: ואנן תנן מן הקרפף ואפילו מן המפוזרין. Ve-anan tenan
min ha-karpef ve-afilu min ha-mefuzarin. We say קרפף karpef is enough even
if they're scattered. So מתניתין יחידה היא. matnitin yechidah hi. No, our
משנה Mishnah is a דעת יחיד dat yachid that says that that's
enough, one criteria, and he's saying that there really is an opposing
opinion that says you need both criteria. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא: beraita: אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Amar Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar. Said רבי שמעון בן אלעזר: Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar: לא נחלקו
בית שמאי ובית הלל על המפוזרין שבשדות שאין מביאים.
lo necheleku Beit Shammai ve-Beit Hillel al
ha-mefuzarin sheba-sadot she-ein mevi'im. Everybody agrees that if it has neither criteria,
it's scattered and it's out in the fields, that you cannot bring
it, that that's מוקצה. muktzah And as תוספות Tosafos pointed out, heck,
it might even be a דאורייתא of gathering. ועל המכונסים שבקרפף, Ve-al
ha-mukhunasin shebe-karpef, and also nobody disagrees about things that have both criteria:
it's gathered in a pile and it's in the קרפף, שמביאים, she-mevi'im,
that that's not מוקצה muktzah. and you can bring it. על מה
נחלקו? Al mah necheleku? What was the debate? על המפוזרין שבקרפף, Al
ha-mefuzarin shebe-karpef, it has only one of the criteria: either it is
scattered and it's in the קרפף. ועל המכונסים שבשדות, Ve-al ha-mukhunasin sheba-sadot,
or it's gathered but it's in the fields. So if you have
one of the two criteria, קרפף or gathered, is one enough to
make it not מוקצה? muktzah שבית שמאי אומרים לא יביא, She-Beit Shammai
omerim lo yavi, you can't bring them, it's מוקצה. muktzah בית הלל
אומרים יביא, Beit Hillel omerim yavi, you can bring them. So what
did the גמרא Gemara prove by this? It proved that according to
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, according to בית הלל,
Beit Hillel, one is enough, which is our משנה. Mishnah. Either gathered
or in the קרפף. But because the ברייתא beraita did not just
say here's a debate of בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, בית הלל, Beit
Hillel, it says רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar believes
this is the debate of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל.
Beit Hillel. So what does everybody else believe? So רב יהודה אמר
שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel is saying that's רבי שמעון בן אלעזר,
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, he's lenient, he thinks it's the debate of
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, and בית הלל Beit
Hillel says one criteria is enough. But רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel is claiming that the opposing position says that בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי Beit Shammai did not debate this case,
and everybody agrees that one criteria is not enough, and that the
only thing that is good is when you have both criteria. Okay,
so that's the issue. Our משנה Mishnah says one criteria is enough,
which we're saying is רבי שמעון בן אלעזר's Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
position of בית הלל, Beit Hillel, and רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel says you need both: it both has to be
gathered and in the קרפף. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר
רבא: Amar Rava: עלי קני ועלי גפנים, alei kanei ve-alei gefanim, if
you're talking about leaves of
reeds or grape leaves, אף על גב דמכנסי, af al gav de-mekhansei,
even if they're gathered up ומותבי ve-motvi and they're sitting in a
pile, כיון דאם מדלי זיקא מבדר להו, keivan de-im madli zika mevader
lehu, since if the wind were to blow they would scatter, כמפוזרין
דמו, ke-mefuzarin damu,
it's like they're scattered, ואסירי ve-asiri and it's forbidden. Like a pile
of leaves. Let's say you raked your yard and you have a
pile of leaves, and you wanted to use those leaves for your
fuel for firewood on יום טוב. Yom Tov, Does that qualify as
מכונסים? mukhunasin? So רבא Rava says whether you need one criteria or
two criteria, we have to determine if that qualifies as מכונסים. mukhunasin.
So רבא Rava says it doesn't. Since it's very easy for the
wind to blow and for it to scatter, we will say that
the fact that they're in a pile is not enough to say
that your דעת da'at was on it, it was on your radar
screen that they would be available to you to use. You didn't
assume they'd be available because it would be so easy for the
wind to scatter it. ואי אתנח מנא מאתמול לעליה, Ve-ee itnach mana
me-etmol la-layeh, but if from the day before you put some
vessel on it, you put some tarp on it or something to
keep it
stable for even if there were to be a wind, a big
rock or something like that, שפיר דמי, shapir dami, then that's fine,
then that shows that you have taken
actions to ensure that it will remain a pile and therefore it's
considered to be something that's on your radar screen, something that you
could expect to have available to you to use. Okay, so right
now we said two things: is one criteria enough or do you
need both? The משנה Mishnah says one criteria is enough: either gathered
or in a קרפף. רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
says no, you need both, the משנה Mishnah is a דעת יחיד,
dat yachid, both gathered and in a קרפף. And then the question
is what constitutes as gathered, and רבא Rava says certain things that
will easily scatter in the wind do not constitute as gathered.
מבדר Mevader scatter?
Yes. מעמר?
עמר? Amar? Yes. Okay, so now we say: איזהו קרפף? Now, now
the question is the debate in the משנה Mishnah between רבי יהודה
and רבי יוסי. רבי יהודה says a קרפף is so close to
the... particularly in terms of Rabbi Yosi's position. So let's take a
look. איבעיא להו, Ibayya lehu, they raised the following question. היכי קאמר,
Heichi ka'amar, what exactly is Rabbi Yosi saying? Is Rabbi Yehuda saying,
what's Rabbi Yosi responding? Is Rabbi Yehuda saying כל שסמוך לעיר והוא
דאית ליה פותחת, Kol shesamuch la'ir vehu de'it lei potachat, is Rabbi
Yehuda assuming that a קרפף has a fence and a lock and
saying in addition to a fence and a lock it also has
to be near a city? We're back to the question of how
many criteria, but now how many criteria do you need to define
something as a קרפף? So it needs both close to the city
and a lock, that's taken for granted. ואתא רבי יוסי למימר, Ve'ata
Rabbi Yosi lemeimar, and Rabbi Yosi is saying no, כיון דאית ליה
פותחת אפילו בתוך תחום שבת נמי, Keivan de'it lei potachat afilu betoch
techum Shabbat nami, if it has a lock there's no criteria of
being near the city. It's all about having a fence and a
lock. And therefore Rabbi Yosi is only being lenient. Rabbi Yehuda says
yes it has a fence and a lock but it needs to
be close to the city, and Rabbi Yosi says I don't need
it to be close to the city. That's one way to read
it. או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say, הכי קאמר, hachi
ka'amar, maybe Rabbi Yehuda is saying something different. He's saying, כל שסמוך
לעיר בין דאית ליה פותחת בין דלית ליה פותחת. Kol shesamuch la'ir
bein de'it lei potachat bein deleit lei potachat.
It's not a question of one criteria or two. It's a question
of which criteria. So Rabbi Yehuda says for me, the determining factor
is near the city. I don't care if it does have a
lock, it doesn't have a lock, if it's near the city that's
a קרפף. Okay, so sometimes I'll be very lenient. If it doesn't
have a lock, I don't care as long as it's close to
the city. If it's far away from the city, having a lock
and a fence won't help it. For me it's all about being
near the city. ואתא רבי יוסי למימר, Ve'ata Rabbi Yosi lemeimar, Rabbi
Yosi comes along and says, אפילו בתוך תחום שבת, Shabbos,
look it could be at the edge of the תחום שבת, Shabbat.
it could be far from the city, ודווקא דאית ליה פותחת, vedavka
de'it lei potachat, but the determining criterion is not close to the
city, the determining criterion is a fence and a lock. אבל לית
ליה פותחת, Aval leit lei potachat, if it doesn't have the fence
and the lock, אפילו סמוך לעיר נמי לא, afilu samuch la'ir nami
lo, even near the city. Okay, so it's a very simple question
of how you read the משנה. Mishnah. One mentions near the city,
the other mentions the lock and far away from the city. So
are they saying, one says the only thing I look at is
near the city and Rabbi Yosi saying the only thing I look
at is having a fence and a lock? Or no, maybe Rabbi
Yehuda says I need both and Rabbi Yosi says hey, as long
as it's got the fence and lock, who needs being next to
a city? So how do you read the משנה? Mishnah? The גמרא
Gemara says, תא שמע, Ta shema, come from here, מדקתני, midekatni, the
משנה Mishnah says, רבי יוסי אומר כל שנתנסן לו בפותחת, Rabbi Yosi
omer kol shenitnasen lo bepotachat, as long as anything that you
go into with a lock, ואפילו בתוך תחום שבת, ve'afilu betoch techum
Shabbat, even within the boundaries of Shabbat, even at the edge of
the boundary, שמע מינה, Shema mina, Rabbi Yosi תרתי לקולא קאמר. tartei
lekula ka'amar. You see from there that Rabbi Yosi says, you know,
either one to be lenient. Meaning if it's got a lock, it
could be at the edge of the city, and even if it
doesn't have a lock, near a city. For him either criteria enough.
And that Rabbi Yehuda feels that no, you need both. Now how
did the גמרא Gemara prove it from the משנה? Mishnah? What in
the line that the גמרא Gemara quoted showed that it was, you
know, that this was the approach, that Rabbi Yehuda demanded both and
Rabbi Yosi said either criteria is enough? So that's why you have
this huge רש"י Rashi and this huge תוספות, Tosafos and they're not
one of these interesting רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos that are coming
to figure out how does this reconcile with some other גמרא Gemara
or what's the conceptual issue here, but it's like how did the
גמרא Gemara prove its answer from the language of the משנה? Mishnah?
It was a very reasonable question. Does Rabbi Yehuda demand two things
and Rabbi Yosi only one, or does Rabbi Yehuda focus on one
criterion and Rabbi Yosi focus on a different criterion? How did you
resolve it from that language? So I'm not going to tell you
their answer, I'm just going to tell you that's what they try
to figure out. Okay, it's not so clear how the גמרא Gemara
resolved it from that language, but the גמרא Gemara resolved that Rabbi
Yehuda demands both and Rabbi Yosi says either criterion is enough. If
it's got a lock it could be far away, if it doesn't
have a lock as long as it's close, that's also
okay. שמע מינה. Shema mina. אמר רב סלא אמר רבי ירמיה, Amar
Rav Sala amar Rabbi Yirmeya, הלכה כרבי יוסי להקל, halacha k'Rabbi Yosi
lehakel, and we rule that way, either criteria's enough to define it
as a קרפף. On the one hand, defining something as a קרפף
we're lenient, as long as it is either close or has a
fence and lock, whereas what you need in order to allow you
to use the sticks, there we're going to go like Rav Yehuda
Amar Shmuel presumably and demand both things, both that it be in
a קרפף and that it be gathered. Fine. All of this is
just another example of מוקצה muktzah, and a question about when is
something considered to be out of my mind and when is it
considered to be accessible? I will say the interesting thing in which
this is different is that until now מוקצה muktzah has mostly been
things that you're like thinking about but you have set aside, right?
Or something brand new like the egg that's born, but other examples
that we've had of מוקצה muktzah are like, you know, the stuff
that you put up on the roof to dry out or you've
put away in storage and you're not planning on going into your
storehouse so you've locked it up. This is מוקצה muktzah. because it's
the opposite, it hasn't got on your radar screen yet. Scattered sticks
out in the field are not so accessible. ciently in your radar
screen. Okay, and therefore it has to be something that so the
problem is that you know and these are like natural things. It's
not like vessels. Vessels are made for human use, they're like automatically
seen as things that are supposed to be used by people. Whereas
things that are part of the natural world, sticks and rocks and
stones, that are not on your radar screen, those are like naturally
מוקצה. muktza They have to be made, brought onto your radar screen,
and something that you could potentially use. So you know you would
think that gathering them is enough, personally I would think that, like
the משנה, Mishnah, not like רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel. Because once you're gathering them, what's the purpose of gathering if
not to use? But again the assumption would be that even if
they're gathered if they remain out in the field they're yet to
be brought in enough under sort of human control, you know, to
be considered the type of thing that can be considered acceptable to
use. But here the problem is it starts on the outside and
it's bringing it into your scope, as opposed to a lot of
other examples of מוקצה muktza. which are things that are naturally within
your scope, food and vessels, you know, and that but you have
somehow done something to push it out. Okay, so that is certainly
worth noticing the difference here.
And the term בתוך התחום besoch hatchum is actually the term used
for to designate that it's further away.
Yeah, that's a little ironic, right? But בתוך התחום besoch hatchum means
anywhere within
the... עד סמוך לעיר, ad samuch la'ir, correct. Okay, so now let's
look at the next משנה. Mishnah. אין מבקעין עצים לא
מן הקורות ולא מן הקורה שנשברה ביום טוב. Ein mevak'in etzim lo
min hakorot velo min hakorah shenishberah beYom Tov. You cannot chop wood
from beams or from a beam that fell down on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. So the beam that fell down on יום טוב, Yom
Tov the problem is obvious. You have this beam in your rafters
and it cracked and fell down on יום טוב. Yom Tov? So
first, I hope nobody is hurt and that the house is okay.
But now you want to make a fire. So the problem with
that is that that is a מוקצה muktza case. When יום טוב
Yom Tov began it was part of your rafters and clearly was
something that was like out of your דעת da'at to be using.
But how about the beams? What exactly is the problem of chopping
wood from beams, just neat beams that were already available beams before
יום טוב? Yom Tov So we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. And
then the next line is, ואין מבקעין, Ve'ein mevak'in, when you do
chop wood, you can't chop it, לא בקרדום ולא במגירה ולא במגל
אלא בקופיץ. lo bekardom velo bemgirah velo bemagal ela bekupitz. Not with
a קרדום, kardom, which is, I don't know how they translate קרדום,
kardom, an axe, and a מגירה mgirah is, רש״י Rashi describes it
as, you ever see those pictures of like the two guys with
this like multi-tooth saw, you know, cutting down a tree? I don't
know what word that...
A crosscut saw.
Is that what it's called? A crosscut saw. And a מגל magal
was a scythe, which is obviously something that's naturally not used for
cutting, but you can use a קופיץ, kupitz, which is like a
hatchet. Is that what they say for a קופיץ? kupitz? An axe?
I thought the קופיץ kupitz was a cleaver. Cleaver.
Oh like a meat cleaver.
Oh yeah, I'm sorry, רש״י Rashi does say that, סכין של קצבים,
sakin shel katzavim,
like something used by butchers. Okay, so what is the reason not?
So רש״י Rashi says, so you know chopping wood with an axe
would seem to be like a natural thing to do. How else
do you chop wood? But again it gets to this עובדא דחול
uvda dechol thing. You know, if you see people using an axe
and using a crossbeam, whatever, you know, you think about that's what
people are doing when they're going out and at work, you know,
if you're out in the field chopping down trees, chopping wood and
so on. And again it gets to, you know, doing מלאכות melakhot
are okay, but it has to have that context of being done
at that sort of domestic context and not in the work-based sort
of context. So if you're using a meat cleaver and you're just
using it to make the wood for the fire, fine, you're sort
of like, you know, making the wood more usable in your home.
But if you're going out to the backyard with an axe, that
already creates a different experiential reality. Okay, so that's not about מוקצה,
muktzah? that's back to עובדא דחול. uvda dechol. Let's take a look
at how the גמרא Gemara understands the first part of the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, so ל״א עמוד ב׳. lamed aleph amud bet. So the
גמרא Gemara first understands that when it said you cannot chop wood
from קורות, korot, from simple beams, what's the problem? They're beams, they're
like logs of wood. So it understands that the problem with that
in the first part of the משנה Mishnah was the same problem
at the bottom: the act of chopping is a problem, meaning somehow
it's not a מוקצה muktzah? issue, but chopping altogether is a problem.
And the גמרא Gemara then doesn't understand. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says, והאמרת רישא אין מבקעין כלל. V'ha'amart reisha
ein mevak'in klal. How could you say at the end that you
can chop as long as you use a meat cleaver? The beginning
says you can't chop wood at all, even from a pre-you know,
even from beams that were around when יום טוב Yom Tov began.
So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, no
no no, that wasn't the point of the רישא. reisha. The רישא
reisha was not the chopping issue, the רישא reisha was a מוקצה
muktzah? issue. חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. Chisuri mechasra vehachi katani. It's missing
some words or you have to understand the context and here's what
we're talking about. אין מבקעין מן הסוור של קורות. Ein mevak'in min
hasavar shel korot. You cannot chop wood from a pile of beams,
and specifically what סוור savar sort of evokes or refers to
is like beams that are set aside for construction. So you've got
a big pile of like nice pre-cut 2x4s and then on יום
טוב Yom Tov, you decide you're going to use them for your
firewood. Well, excuse me, that's מוקצה. muktzah. Those are things that are
set aside for construction. Okay, so that's the
problem. Where were we? Okay, so מן הסואר של קורות min haso'ar
shel korot ולא מן הקורה שנשברה ביום טוב. v'lo min hakora shenishbera
b'yom tov. Those are things that are מוקצה muktzah. because they began
יום טוב Yom Tov, they were not going to be used, they
were set aside for some other purpose. אבל מבקעין מן הקורה שנשברה
מערב יום טוב aval mevakin min hakora shenishbera me'erev Yom Tov but
if it's a beam that broke on ערב יום טוב Erev Yom
Tov or we would say, you know, if you have a woodshed
where you keep your logs of wood for firewood, that you can
chop. Because that's not מוקצה. muktzah וכשמבקעין, uk'shem mevakin, now let's talk
about the act of chopping. When you get around to chopping it,
אין מבקעין לא בקרדום ולא במגל ולא במגירה אלא בקופיץ. ein mevakin
lo b'kardom v'lo b'maga v'lo b'magaira ela b'kupitz. You can only chop
it with a cleaver, not with these things which are much more
as רש״י Rashi says כלי אומנות, kli umnus, like a type of
craftsman vessel and much more of an עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. תניא
נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we talked similarly, אין מבקעין עצים לא
מן הסואר של קורות. ein mevakin eitzim lo min haso'ar shel korot.
So it doesn't just say מן הקורה, min hakora, which is ambiguous,
which could mean logs of wood, the specific use of the word
סואר so'ar refers to a pile that as I said is like
a pile set aside for construction
purposes. So the ברייתא Baraita makes it clear that that's the context,
ולא מן הקורה שנשברה ביום טוב v'lo min hakora shenishbera b'yom tov
and not from the beam that broke on יום טוב, Yom Tov
לפי שאינו מן המוכן l'fi she'eino min hamuchan and it says explicitly
the problem of the first case is a מוקצה muktzah. problem, it
is not set aside for use. Now we get to the chopping
problem, ולא בקרדום, v'lo b'kardom, not with an axe. אמר רב
חיננא בר שמיה משמיה דרב: Amar Rav Chinena bar Shamaya mishmei d'Rav:
לא שנו אלא בנקבות שלו אבל בזכרות שלו מותר. lo shanu ela
b'nekeivoh shelo aval b'zachros shelo mutar. The problem is only with the
feminine part of the axe, but the male part is okay. Now
I have to tell you, I understand when you're dealing with masculine
things that, yes, thank you,
like you know like what were the things we dealt with in
סוכה? Sukkah? Like pipes. You know there could be like a male
part and a female part. You know by something that is serrated
and that's an axe, right, if you want to sort of use
that imagery, the male part is the part that protrudes and that's
doing the cutting, so how you gonna cut something with a female
part? So I didn't really get how רש״י Rashi was trying to
explain it, I saw but somehow when it refers to the female
part, it's stuff that is not as broader point, not as fine
points, and again it refers to the part that is more used
in the context of it being a כלי אומנות kli umnus like
a type of a craftsman vessel and not something that is just
for home-based cutting. So he says that when this hatchet is a
problem, it's only a problem using the נקבות שבו nekeivoh shebo that
part which is again more for the chopping in the field
and more for the craftsman type of use, אבל בזכרות שלו aval
b'zachros shelo the narrower part of it, that is מותר mutar that's
permissible, because that's more like a meat cleaver and that's more like
a home-based type of a cutting. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא,
p'shita, that's obvious, בקופיץ תנן, b'kupitz tnan, I don't even know what
it's talking about, but if you know what it's talking about maybe
it's obvious. בקופיץ תנן: b'kupitz tnan: our משנה Mishnah says you can
use a cleaver, and this part of the hatchet is like a
cleaver. So if this part of the hatchet is like a cleaver,
what should the problem be? Now of course the problem is עובדא
דחול, uvda d'chol, it's obvious what the problem should be, it doesn't
matter which part you're using it matters what type of experience it's
evoking. So the גמרא Gemara says you think you know what it's
talking about? Let's first read the answer then you can tell me
what you're thinking. מהו דתימא, ma d'teima, I might have thought הני
מילי בקופיץ לחודיה, hanei mili b'kupitz l'chudai, it's one thing to use
something that's just
a cleaver, אבל קרדום וקופיץ, aval kardom v'kupitz, something that's like a
combo, a hatchet, an axe that also has a part of it
that's like a קופיץ, kupitz, אימא מיגו דהאי גיסא אסור, eima migu
d'hai gisa asur, since you can't use this part of the axe,
רש״י Rashi
so says
there's a wide side and a narrow side, like a front and
a back, but if you can't use it with one part of
it, האי גיסא נמי אסור, hai gisa nami asur, using the other
part of it is also forbidden, קמשמע לן k'mashma lan that that's
not true, that you can use the part that functions like a
cleaver. Now I gotta tell you, my sympathy is with the position
that it should be forbidden. If the issue here is עובדא דחול,
uvda d'chol, then experientially somebody looking at you you're looking at you're
doing it with this type of an
instrument, that's the problem of the experience, and that's what the גמרא
Gemara sort of winds up saying at the end. ואיכא דמתני לה
אסיפא, v'ika d'matni la asayfa, somehow this discussion at the end of
the משנה, Mishnah, not to sort of say not all axes are
a problem, but to say there are even some cleavers that will
be a problem. Okay, אלא בקופיץ, ela b'kupitz, you're allowed to use
a cleaver. אמר רב חיננא בר שמיה משמיה דרב: Amar Rav Chinena
bar Shamaya mishmei d'Rav: לא שנו אלא בזכרות שלו, lo shanu ela
b'zachros shelo, apparently cleaver also had a section that was narrower and
wider. and when you can use a cleaver, that's only in the
male part of it, the narrower part of it, which again is
more a different type of a chopping that's done out in the
woods, but אבל בנקבתו שלו aval b'nikevato shelo in the female part
of it, אסור. assur. That's forbidden because that's more similar to like
an axe type of a cutting. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא,
pshita, it's obvious, again I know what that means. Anyway, ולא בקרדום
תנן, ve-lo b'kardum t'nan, it says you can't use an axe. So
if you can't use an axe, presumably you can't use the axe-like
part of the cleaver. No, מהו דתימא, ma d'teima, no, I might
have thought הני מילי קרדום, hani mili kardum, that's something that's totally
an axe. But קופיץ דקרדום, kupitz d'kardum, something that's a cleaver and
an axe, אימא מיגו דהאי גיסא שרי, eima migu d'hai gisa shari,
maybe I should say if you're going to let me use one
part of the cleaver, האי גיסא נמי שרי, hai gisa nami shari,
you should let me use the other part of the cleaver. קמשמע
לן kamashma lan that you don't. That you don't use the part
of the cleaver that functions like an axe. So this approach is
more מחמיר, machmir, says an axe is out completely which makes sense,
it keeps to the chopping concern and even a cleaver you can
only use it in the cleaver-like function as a bit and not
the axe-like function of it.
Yes, I have a theory.
Do you have a theory what's going on here?
Yes, it looks like, I think it looks like this, just the
meat cleaver, all right? Meat cleaver, I'm not good, you're a much
better drawer than I. This is a meat cleaver, right? Yep. Okay,
got the, right, that's smooth. Yep. So this is a thing that's
got two sides to
it.
So you see the female, the male is... you think it's serrated
and non-serrated? Correct.
So you think...
so you basically think זכר zachar means serrated and נקבה nekeva means
like a sharp single point non-serrated.
Well, it certainly is true that the difference between an axe and
a home-based knife could very well be, an axe clearly is non-serrated
and a home-based knife is.
But so maybe they had an implement that looked like that, right,
that could be. Okay, the picture Steinsaltz has of a what he
says is a Roman dolabra,
okay, does
not seem to fit this discussion at all.
All right, anyway, I think we get the idea. Let's go on
now to the next משנה. mishnah. Okay, בית, bayis, you see these
סוגיא sugya other than knowing what they're talking about in terms of
reality are
very... have been much more straightforward than some of the earlier סוגיא.
sugya. Okay, בית שמלא פירות. bayis she-malei peiros. You have a house
that is filled with fruit. Now, again, house filled with fruit, you
think about my living room, I got it filled with apples, but
presumably, basically think about it as you've got a storage facility. You've
got a shed and it's filled with fruit and fruit could mean
apples, but fruit could also mean wheat, okay, whatever it is. Anyway,
you've got your storage shed that's filled with fruit. So this by
the way, no, this by the way gets us, makes us think
about the discussion before about מתחילין באוצר תחילה, matchilin b'otzar techilah, right?
Can you break into a to start using food that's been stored
away, or until you've begun using it before יום טוב, Yom Tov,
maybe it's מוקצה? muktzah. It's put away into storage. But let's take
a look what the issue here is. Here the issue is not
going to be the use of the fruit itself, presumably this doesn't
have a status of אוצר otzar or it assumes that you can
begin using an אוצר. otzar. So the issue is not the fruit
itself, the issue is getting to the fruit. Okay, so it was
that it was filled with it but the house was locked is
the idea before יום טוב Yom Tov, began and there was no
access to the fruit. נפחת, nifchas, and then it sort of a
breached, something broke in the wall and now you have access to
the fruit. נוטל ממקום הפחת, notel mimakom hapachas,
you can get fruit from, you can go into it from where
there's a breach in the wall. רבי מאיר אומר אף פוחת לכתחילה
ונוטל. Rabbi Meir omer af poches l'chatchilah venotel. Big חידוש chiddush of
this משנה mishnah is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says you can
break into the house, break the wall and get the fruit. Now,
רש"י Rashi says why, before we get to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
which will be the focus of the גמרא, Gemara, why is it
not מוקצה? muktzah If it wasn't accessible, forget the idea of אוצר,
otzar, if it wasn't accessible because it was blocked off in a
house, why is it that
it's... why... why is it not מוקצה? muktzah. So רש"י Rashi says
because the only obstacle to getting at it was breaking the wall,
and as we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, breaking the wall might
have only been a rabbinic issue, and that's not enough to make
it מוקצה. muktzeh תוספות Tosafot. is not happy with that. תוספות Tosafot
who cares, besides textual evidence, who cares if it's off-limits because of
a biblical issue or a rabbinic issue? It was something that was
out of your reach. So if it's out of your reach, even
if breaking the wall is only rabbinic, it should be מוקצה. muktzeh.
So תוספות Tosafot says we must assume that our משנה mishnah is
like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who basically doesn't hold of מוקצה muktzeh
or who holds of a much smaller category of מוקצה. muktzeh? Okay,
so but the first part of the משנה mishnah is it's not
מוקצה. muktzeh Why not? רש"י Rashi comes up with this new idea
because it's only a rabbinic restriction is the only obstacle and that's
not enough to make it מוקצה muktzeh if it becomes accessible. And
תוספות Tosafot just says it's a position that doesn't hold of מוקצה.
muktzeh. But the focus of the גמרא Gemara is going to be
the last line of are you allowed to break into the house
to get to the fruit. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. By the way, this is somewhat similar to the question
of destroying packages on שבת, Shabbat. okay, but destroying packages on שבת
Shabbat to get to the food
is... easier issue because destroying a package is hard to categorize what
מלאכה it is. The issue comes up if I open the package
in a way that makes it a functional vessel, like is opening
the bottle caps does that make it now a functional כלי? kli?
Or does opening like the old-fashioned milk cartons, right, make it a
כלי? kli? But to completely destroy it by, like, tearing open a
bag of potato chips, like basically nobody feels that that's a problem.
But when you're dealing with a structure, then destroying it is a
problem of סותר. soter. So in the one way, it's similar to
an issue of שבת, Shabbat, but on the other way, this particular
example is a more serious one and we'll have to see how
it gets discussed. Did you have a question?
I just was bothered by the, you know, we're translating this משנה
Mishna as if it's saying ונפתח, veniftach, like it was breached, but
it's נפחת, niphchat, and it must mean the same but it's a
language I've never seen before, right? Yeah. Yeah.
I mean, it is true. Is it חסר chaser אותיות osyos
or it's been diminished?
Diminished. Right. Like something fell, like, I understand it means that something
like fell off of it and now there's a breach, an opening.
Well,
נפתח niftach means like the door is open. נפחת niphchat means like
the wall fell down.
Right, but it's not like a... it's not like a pierce... it's
not like a— Yeah.
I don't know exactly. I understand like something like the wall fell
down. Like a wall collapsed or something. Alright, but it's a good
point. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So the
גמרא Gemara wants to understand how can you break into this? Again,
it's not like a bag of potato chips. אמאי? Amai? Why does
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir let you break into it? והא קסתר אהלא?
Veha kasasar ahala? You're destroying an אהל. ohel. You're destroying a structure,
you know, an edifice. אהל Ohel here means less not so much
the roof, but like an edifice, and therefore it's סותר, soter, because
we're not, you know, that's a מלאכה. אמר רב נחומי בר אדא
אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Nechumi bar Ada amar Shmuel: באווירא דליבני. Be'avira
delivnei. We're talking here about literally means the air of bricks, but
what it means is you have stacked bricks that—but they are not
being held together by mortar. And therefore to take them apart is
not really סותר soter because there's nothing that is like permanently keeping
it around, which could explain why it was נפחת niphchat also, maybe
it collapsed because it doesn't have any mortar. So therefore
it's not really destroying. Now that's fascinating because even if there's no
mortar, who was it? I remember we were learning when we were
discussing this I think in עירובין Eruvin or some—you know, somebody told
me about how it's, you know, it came up in the גמרא
Gemara and I think it was Wolfson or somebody mentioned, you know,
how they have these like stone fences or walls in Europe and
in England that were made with absolutely no mortar. That's true. But
it was—but there was this real skill of how to fit the
stones and the stuff has lasted like hundreds and hundreds of years.
That's true. Right. So, you know, so you can make something that
is pretty darn stable without mortar. Now maybe it's different. Stones are
irregularly shaped and if you know how to use them, if you
want to use just simple bricks which are very regularly shaped and
there's no mortar, it's not going to be as stable as a
brick. But nevertheless, you would think at least דרבנן derabbanan this has
to be some type of סותר, soter, even if not biblical. So
let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with it. So the גמרא
Gemara says והאמר רב נחמן, Veha amar Rav Nachman, doesn't רב נחמן
Rav Nachman
say הני ליבני דיתמי מבניינא, Hani livni deyasmi mibinyana, if there are
bricks that are left over from a construction site, okay? So now
we're back to the מוקצה muktzeh case. Remember we had before the
beams on a construction site? Now we have leftover bricks. The difference
are that the beams were not yet used; the bricks are leftover.
So you have a pile of leftover bricks at a construction site.
שרי לטלטולינהו בשבתא, Shari letiltulinhu beshabta, you can move them on שבת,
Shabbat. they're not מוקצה. muktzeh! Why? So on the one hand, they're
no longer going to be used for construction, so it's not like
they're מוקצה muktzah. from that perspective. Okay, but what reasonable use do
you have for them that would make them not מוקצה? muktzah, הואיל
וחזי למיזגא עלייהו, Ho'il vechazi lemizga aleihu, because you can lie down
on them. So therefore
they're no longer—they're leftover, so they're not מוקצה muktzah for that reason,
and they're also not מוקצה muktzah? because they're not unusable because no,
if you've got bricks lying around you'll use them to sit on,
right? You know, that happens sometimes, especially people in Manhattan, right, they
go out, they have lunch, they sit on, you know, on steps
or whatever, you have a nice rock, you sit on a rock.
So, and presumably that would be a natural use, and therefore they're
not מוקצה. muktzah Now why is that—now so far it's not clear
what the question is. So here's the next part of the statement.
שרגנהו, Shargineihu, if however you piled them up and put them all
back in a pile, you know, in like a nice stacked pile,
אקצינהו, aktsineihu, then you've made them מוקצה Muktzah again because you stack
them all up very nice, it means now you're going to—you're setting
them aside to be used in another construction purpose. You know, they're
not just there for sitting on and using. So what's the question?
So the question is—it's very funny, you know. The גמרא Gemara says,
"Oh, we're talking about a house that's made with bricks that has
no plaster and therefore you can break into it." So my response
would be, "Isn't that at least דרבנן derabbanan of סותר?" soter? The
גמרא's Gemara question is, "But wait, it's still מוקצה!" muktzah Because we
just—we have this teaching that if you stack up bricks you make
them, you know, even if... leftover bricks, you've made them מוקצה.
muktzah Even before, you stacked them up before יום טוב, Yom Tov
right.
So here, that's stacking them up because you're gonna use them for
something, for some construction certainly. If you stacked them up to create
a type of a shed, that makes them מוקצה, muktzah, that makes
them off-limits. Exactly. So that's the גמרא's Gemara question. How can you
still break into it if it's still a מוקצה muktzah, problem? So
אמר רבי זירא, Amar Reb Zera, so רבי זירא Reb Zera says,
ביום טוב אמרו אבל לא בשבת. Be-Yom Tov amru aval lo be-Shabbat.
We're talking about יום טוב, Yom Tov not about שבת. Shabbat And
therefore what? So what? Isn't it still מוקצה? muktzah, So the answer
seems to be that again, the same way we've given other areas
of latitude on יום טוב Yom Tov. for the sake of food
preparation—and let's not forget that according to the תורה Torah you're allowed
to do מלאכות on יום טוב Yom Tov. for food preparation—that we
will waive מוקצה muktzah concerns if it is directly relevant to getting
access to food and to getting food. And look at תוספות. אמר
רבי זירא ביום טוב שנו, Amar Reb Zera be-Yom Tov shanu, the
tiny תוספות at the bottom. He says, פירוש שהתירו מוקצה משום אוכל
נפש אבל לא בשבת מכאן יש ראיה לריצב"א שפירש לעיל דטלטול מוקצה
התירו ביום טוב משום אוכל נפש, Perush she-hitiru muktzah mishum okhel nefesh
aval lo be-Shabbat mikan yesh ra'aya le-Ritzba she-perush le'el de-tiltul muktzah hitiru
be-Yom Tov mishum okhel nefesh, right, which is quite fascinating because more
we've sort of been finding things that are like, you know, very
local allowances or things that are more like local categories. Cooking is
a category that's about food. מוקצה muktzah seems to be this like,
you know, very broad-based thing. So, and so here becomes a, you
know, and to sort of say well, if it's getting in the
way of preparing food, we can waive a מוקצה muktzah concern. How
far can you take this? It's a very interesting question. Certainly not
to eat the food, right, because this is something that's an obstacle
to getting to the food. Right, so much of what we talked
about before with these מוקצה muktzah issues. Right, so if you're, if
your food is—if your
food is מוקצה, muktzah that's the first משנה. Mishnah. Your food is
מוקצה, muktzah the egg. So we're not going to let you—if the
food itself is מוקצה, muktzah. we're not going to let you ignore
that. But if מוקצה's muktzeh. somehow an obstacle to you getting to
the food, then we're going to. But again, think about all of
the early משניות Mishnayot like מתחילין באוצר תחילה, matchilin be-otzar techila, all
these other types of things which seem to sort of say that
מוקצה muktzeh, concerns remained relevant concerns even in the context of food.
And תוספות here is saying that they don't, so how to make
all of that work together is not so clear. Yes.
Wait, also רש"י Rashi also says, seems to take the same—Yes, רש"י
Rashi says yes.
He just—תוספות just makes a point of it.
Yes. Right, it's really interesting the way you conceptualize it. I would
have thought the opposite. In other words, if you—שמחת יום טוב simchat
Yom Tov more than the food itself. Right. These are like מכשירי
אוכל נפש, machshirei okhel nefesh, right? I have to get at the
food.
Yes, but I was more talking about—Yeah, it's
really interesting what you say.
But the reason is because if the food itself is off-limits, then
it's like not food that's supposed to be used for יום טוב.
Yom Tov You know, that sort of more disqualifies it. We don't
want to, you know, whereas if the food itself is okay to
eat and the מוקצה muktzeh,
is preventing you, that seems to be the difference. But again, you
have to say how does this work into the discussions of מתחילין
באוצר, matchilin be-otzar, all the earlier discussions. Anyway, here the גמרא Gemara
seems to say we—we ignore the מוקצה muktzeh concerns. At least רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir does. Maybe that's one answer, that this is רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir ignores the מוקצה muktzeh concerns
and—to allow you to get access to the food.
Although רש"י Rashi seems to turn the bricks into rocks.
רש"י Rashi of the גמרא. Gemara.
סידרא של אבנים בלא טיט.
Sidra
shel avanim belo tit.
That's a good point.
Okay, so anyway, let's—so now let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara.
תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hakhi ותמי לי u-tzmili רבי מאיר אומר
אף פוחת לכתחילה ונוטל ביום טוב. Rabbi Meir omer af pokhet lekhatchila
ve-notel be-Yom Tov. אמרו לו—say, Amru lo אמרו ליה, amru leh, they
said, I'm sorry, excuse me, I misread that. אף פוחת לכתחילה ונוטל.
ביום טוב אמרו אבל לא בשבת. Af pokhet lekhatchila ve-notel. Be-Yom Tov
amru aval lo be-Shabbat. So the ברייתא Baraita clearly says that רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir היתר heter is limited to יום טוב. Yom Tov
And יום טוב Yom Tov. we know we allow more for the
sake of food. And that's why he's allowing it and according to
the גמרא Gemara what it's doing is it's allowing מוקצה muktzeh? issues.
If you were to have asked me, I would have more said
it allows סותר דרבנן, soter derabbanan, right, allows the fact somehow we'll
say it's not biblical סותר, soter, it's a temporary, it's not plaster.
But that's what's sort of being given a license to, whereas the
גמרא Gemara sort of more frames it in terms of the מוקצה.
muktzeh Okay. אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. Now says שמואל. Shmuel. Now this
is a very important in terms of defining issues of בונה boneh
and סותר. soter. So we turn a little bit away from יום
טוב Yom Tov into a more broader discussion. חותמות שבקרקע. Khotamot she-ba-karka.
If you have seals on the ground, basically what you have to
think about this is—they had wells, and think about like a manhole
cover. Okay, you got a manhole cover to a well. And what
do you do to make sure the manhole cover doesn't—you know, walk
away, meaning somebody doesn't take it for their collection of manhole covers
or it doesn't just accidentally get lost. So you have it roped
down and—or chained like they have sort of at the bank, you
know, with the pens chained down. You have it chained and connected
to the well, and that's how you keep the manhole cover connected
to the well. So this is what you've got on שבת. Shabbat
So, חותמות שבקרקע מתיר. khotamot she-ba-karka mattir. You can undo it to
get access to the well. It's not like you can lift it
up—you know, let's assume that it's chained in multiple places. Okay, so
or knotted or roped in. And of course it's not going to
be a קשר של קיימא Kesher shel kayama because the whole point
of it is that it's to open it. So it's the type
of a knot that's used for undoing and doing. So it's not
a problem of קשר של קיימא Kesher shel kayama of קשר kesher
of undoing and knotting. The other thing it's not a problem of
is taking apart a structure. Even though this is roped on, why
is it not taking apart a structure? Because, yes, but why is
it not taking apart a structure if it's roped on and you're
undoing a connection and it's no longer connected? Well, okay, you're going
to put it back on and because, you know, the more precise
way of thinking or framing it is like this is how it's
meant to be used, right? Like nobody sort of says like when
I close a door somehow I've like בונה boneh because I've now
like added a part of the wall. Oh, but it's not really
בונה boneh because it was already attached before. I mean, yes, that's
true, but to some degree this is just this is how you
use the structure. This is how you use the well is you
open it up by undoing it, so it doesn't really create a
structural change even though physically for the time being it's not connected.
That's allowed that you can undo the knot.
Okay, אבל לא מפקיע ולא חותך. Aval lo mafki'a velo chotech. What
you cannot do is unravel the rope, like, you know, it's one
of those braided strings, or cut the rope. Okay, now you'll say,
look, physically you're doing the same thing. Physically you're detaching the cover
from the well. But no, there's a big difference because now you're
doing it, a, in a way that makes it hard to put
it back and b, in a way that really like I said,
it's not the way in which it's intended to be used. You
have structurally changed it, even though in both cases the cover is
not attached. In the first case it's not attached but as, you
know, you said, David, it's in the process of coming back on
and this is all seen as still combined in the same structure.
Here you have really severed their relationship, not just in the physical
way and therefore that is considered סותר, soter, a type of deconstructing
of a structure. What does מפקיע mafki'a mean? מפקיע Mafki'a means to
take out? No, מפקיע mafki'a means to unbraid the rope. Unbraid the
rope. Yeah. Gotcha. Okay. So that's what he says, very important here
in terms of thinking about issues of סותר. soter. Now שבכלים, shebekeilim,
if you have something like that in a vessel, you've got like
a little, you know, box at home, you've got, I don't know,
like a box by your bed, you know, a locker and it's
got this cover of it also that's kept on by ropes, so
מתיר מפקיע וחותך. matir mafki'a vechotech. That you can even cut the
rope. Why? Because this is a principle of אין בונה וסותר בכלים.
ein boneh vesoter bekeilim. The idea, it's sort of like I talked
before, there's a big difference of knocking down a house to get
to the food and tearing open a bag of potato chips to
get to the food. Okay, סותר soter is an issue by structures.
סותר soter is not an issue by כלים. keilim. Okay, and therefore
it is okay to destroy the vessel, that's like tearing open your
potato chip bag. That's okay, but it's not okay when you're dealing
with the well and with a structure connected to the ground. Okay,
yeah. אחד שבת ואחד יום טוב. Echad Shabbat ve-echad Yom Tov. And
this doesn't matter שבת Shabbat or יום טוב. Yom Tov? Even on
שבת, Shabbat. you're allowed to be
חותך chotech and if it's a כלי, kli, which again gets to
opening your potato chips in a destructive way on שבת. Shabbat Okay,
מיתיבי, Meitivei, says the גמרא, Gemara, let me ask you about this.
חותמות שבקרקע, Chotamot shebakarka, we have a ברייתא Braitah that says the
following: חותמות שבקרקע, chotamot shebakarka,
again these like manhole covers on the ground, בשבת מתיר, beShabbat matir,
on שבת Shabbat you can undo the knot, אבל aval again it's
not a permanent knot, אבל לא מפקיע ולא חותך, aval lo mafki'a
velo chotech, but you can't cut the rope. So far so good.
ביום טוב מתיר מפקיע וחותך, beYom Tov matir mafki'a vechotech, but on
יום טוב Yom Tov.
you can even cut the rope. Okay, now how could that be?
This is a structure connected to the ground. How are we letting
you cut the rope and change it and structurally destroy it or
deconstruct it on יום טוב? Yom Tov,
So the גמרא Gemara says הא מני רבי מאיר היא, Ha mani
Rabbi Meir hi, this is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דאמר אף פוחת
לכתחילה ונוטל, de-amar af poches lechatchilah venotel, that you can break into
the house and to get the food. So therefore you can do
סותר soter to get the food. And here too you can do
סותר soter to get the water in the well. ופליגי רבנן עליה,
Ufligi rabanan aleih, and the Rabbis argue on it, him. ואנא דאמרי
כרבנן, Ve-ana d'amri kerabanan, I say like the Rabbis that don't let
you do סותר. soter. Now of course the problem is is that
we've explained רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that he wasn't real סותר, soter,
that it was a case of not, you know, unplastered stacked bricks.
So therefore how here are we going to, now that we say
that you can really do what seems to be a permanent סותר
soter or סותר soter of a permanent structure, we're going to now
have to re-understand רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay, but that's what he
is saying. So now the גמרא Gemara says ומי פליגי רבנן עליה
בחותמות שבקרקע? Umi pligi rabanan aleih bechotamot shebakarka? Do the Rabbis really
disagree with him? והתניא, Vehatanya, in this case of manhole covers, we
taught in a ברייתא, Braitah, מודים חכמים לרבי מאיר בחותמות שבקרקע, Modim
Chachamim le-Rabbi Meir bechotamot shebakarka, the Rabbis agree to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir in the seals on the ground, שבשבת מתיר אבל לא מפקיע
ולא חותך, shebeShabbat matir aval lo mafki'a velo chotech, that on שבת
Shabbat you can undo the knot like So the Rabbis will say
it's one thing breaking into the structure, but cutting the cover, that
you're allowed to do on יום טוב. Yom Tov? So now we've
got two questions. Number one is why is cutting the cover off
different than breaking down the wall? And number two is why is
this allowed on יום טוב, Yom Tov, whatever happened to סותר? soter?
So we don't have an answer to that yet, but we've got
a ברייתא Baraita that says cutting the cover's okay. So how can
he say we say that cutting the cover is not good even
on יום טוב? Yom Tov So it says top of ל''ב ע''א,
Lamed Bet Amud Aleph, הוא דאמר כי האי תנא, hu d'amar ki
hai tanna, he says like the following תנא tanna דתניא, de-tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: חותמות שבקרקע, chotamot she-be-karka, again these covers
on the ground, on the wells,
מתיר, matir, you can undo the knot, אבל לא מפקיע ולא חותך,
aval lo mafkia ve-lo choteich, you cannot cut the rope, אחד שבת
ואחד יום טוב, echad Shabbat ve-echad Yom Tov, whether שבת Shabbat. or
יום טוב, Yom Tov either way. So we do have a ברייתא
Baraita that says that יום טוב Yom Tov. is the same and
you cannot cut the rope on יום טוב Yom Tov the same
way you can't do it on שבת. Shabbat. ושבכלי, ve-she-bi-kli, now if
it's a vessel, בשבת מתיר אבל לא מפקיע ולא חותך, be-Shabbat matir
aval lo mafkia ve-lo choteich, now this is going to be more
מחמיר machmir though, not in the you know, in the vessel case
as well, not just more מחמיר machmir on the manhole cover on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. If it's a vessel, then on שבת Shabbat?
you can undo the knot, but you can't cut it. ביום טוב
מתיר ומפקיע וחותך, be-Yom Tov matir u-mafkia ve-choteich, and on יום טוב
Yom Tov you can even cut the rope. So now the גמרא
Gemara is going to say: That ברייתא Baraita doesn't all work like
you. תירצת לך רישא, tiratzta lecha reisha, the first part of the
ברייתא Baraita works like you. It says that when it comes to
the manhole cover, that you can't do even on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. ואלא סיפא קשיא, ve-ella seifa kashya, the end of the ברייתא
Baraita doesn't work like you, because the end of the ברייתא Baraita
says that when it comes to a vessel, you said vessel's fine,
destroy the vessel, cut it, I don't care, שבת Shabbat. יום טוב
Yom Tov doesn't matter, open up the bag of potato chips. But
this ברייתא Baraita says that when it comes to, even in the
vessel case, on שבת Shabbat you're not allowed to cut the rope.
So the end of the ברייתא Baraita doesn't work like you. So
the גמרא Gemara says: No. הא מני רבי נחמיה היא. ha manni
Rabbi Nechemya hi. The end of the ברייתא Baraita is רבי נחמיה
Rabbi Nechemya and it has nothing to do with a problem of
סותר. soter. It's a רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya that has a completely
different issue, which is why he doesn't want you to cut the
rope on שבת. What's his different issue? So דאמר: de-amar: כל הכלים
אין ניטלין אלא דרך תשמישן. kol ha-kelim ein nitalim ella derech tashmishan.
So רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya is in an extreme position in the
world of מוקצה. muktzeh, And what רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya says is
even a normal vessel like your knife in the kitchen, which you
would say is absolutely not מוקצה, muktzeh, he says even your knife
in the kitchen is only allowed to use for what a kitchen
knife is usually used for. And you cannot use your kitchen knife
to cut the rope on your vessel. You can't use your kitchen
knife to scratch an itch. You can't use your kitchen knife to
pick your teeth. The only thing you do with a kitchen knife
is what it is normally used for is for cutting food, you
know, that is being served or whatever. So therefore he says, look,
in principle you're destroying a vessel like tearing open the bag of
potato chips, that's allowed to get to food, that's allowed on שבת.
And that's what I said. Why does this ברייתא Baraita say that
you can't cut the rope on שבת? Because that's רבי נחמיה, Rabbi
Nechemya, who it's not about the destruction part, it's about using a
knife to cut a rope, and a knife is not supposed to
be used for cutting ropes. You know, a knife is supposed to
be used for the kitchen knife. Now maybe you have a knife
that's used for cutting ropes, but that might be מוקצה, muktzeh, okay?
Because knives that aren't מוקצה muktzeh, aren't set aside for cutting ropes.
Okay, he says, the גמרא Gemara says: One minute. אי רבי נחמיה,
iei Rabbi Nechemya, if it's רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemya, מאי איריא שבת?
mai irya Shabbat? So that issue of not using your knife for
some different purpose is not simply limited to שבת. אפילו יום טוב
נמי? afilu Yom Tov nami? He presumably has a problem even about
what you use your vessels for on יום טוב. Yom Tov So
the גמרא Gemara says: וכי תימא שאני ליה לרבי נחמיה בין שבות
דשבת לשבות דיום טוב? ve-ki teima shani leh le-Rabbi Nechemya bein shevut
de-Shabbat le-shevut de-Yom Tov? And if you say maybe רבי נחמיה Rabbi
Nechemya would distinguish, maybe he'd be more strict on שבת about using
vessels only for their intended use, maybe on יום טוב Yom Tov,
he'd be more lenient. ומי שאני ליה? u-mi shani leh? Does he
really make a distinction? והתניא חדא, ve-ha tanya chada, one ברייתא Baraita
teaches: מסיקין בכלים ואין מסיקין בשברי כלים. masikin be-kelim ve-ein masikin be-shivrei
kelim.
Now this is clearly יום טוב Yom Tov. because it talks about
using fuel for a fire. So what type of things can you
use for a fire? What is מוקצה muktzeh and what's not מוקצה?
muktzeh. So according to one ברייתא, Baraita, it's a very interesting thing.
You can take a nice whole vessel, you can take, I don't
know, a chair, thank you, and throw it in the fire. But
if your chair broke on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can't throw
it in the fire. Why not? That's the more natural thing, because
it broke on יום טוב. Yom Tov So since it broke on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, then it became מוקצה muktzeh, once it broke.
Even though we say why become מוקצה, why didn't it turn into
firewood? But nevertheless, the chair isn't מוקצה, so once you have something
not מוקצה, use it for firewood. But broken chair if it broke
on יום טוב is מוקצה, don't use it for fire. ותניא אידך,
ve-tanya idach, so that's a position that holds of מוקצה and distinguishes
between the chair and the broken chair. ותניא אידך, ve-tanya idach, we
taught another ברייתא: Baraita: מסיקין בין בכלים בין בשברי כלים, masikin bein
be-kelim bein be-shivrei kelim, you can even use the broken chair, okay?
Why is that? So that is the position, is presumably is the
position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that doesn't hold of מוקצה. So
even if it broke on יום טוב, it's not מוקצה, it's not
נולד, nolad, it's not a problem. Fine. ותניא אידך *V'tanya idach*, and
then we have a third ברייתא *Brayta* that says אין מסיקין לא
בכלים ולא בשברי כלים *ein masiqin lo b'keilim v'lo b'shivrei keilim*. Not
only can you not use the broken chair because it's נולד *nolad*
and מוקצה *muktzah*, you can't even use the chair. Now why can't
you use the chair? ומשני *um'shani* and we answered לא קשיא *lo
kashya*. הא רבי יהודה *Ha Rabbi Yehuda*, the first position is רבי
יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* who holds of מוקצה *muktzah* and distinguishes between the
chair and the broken chair. הא רבי שמעון *Ha Rabbi Shimon*, the
second one that lets you use both is רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon*,
he can even use a broken chair, he doesn't hold of מוקצה
*muktzah*. הא רבי נחמיה *Ha Rabbi Nechemia*, the third one doesn't let
you use the chair is רבי נחמיה *Rebbe Nechemia*. Now because chairs
aren't firewood. But now we have a problem. This is יום טוב
*Yom Tov* because we're talking about firewood. So you see רבי נחמיה
*Rebbe Nechemia* has his issue even by יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So
how come you think that the ברייתא *Brayta* that says don't cut
the rope, that the first part is based on רבי נחמיה *Rebbe
Nechemia*, isn't it... but then why does it allow it on יום
טוב *Yom Tov*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says תרי תנאי *trei tanna'ei*
אליבא דרבי נחמיה *aliba d'Rebbe Nechemia*, fine, there'll be a debate whether
רבי נחמיה *Rebbe Nechemia* would say his position about not using a
vessel for a non-intended use, would he say it on יום טוב
*Yom Tov* as well? One approach says he would, one approach says
he would not. I want to tell you though that we are
still left with a big unanswered question, which is we started by
asking isn't it סותר *soter*? And then at the end we sort
of said okay but according to a ברייתא *Brayta* you can actually
cut the rope on the cover of the manhole to get access
to the water and we're not concerned with סותר *soter* and it
compared it to the, you know, to the case of the what
do you call it, to the case of breaking into the house.
And so why is that allowed? Why isn't that a מלאכה דאורייתא
*melacha de'oraita*? Now there could be answers, maybe you could say, you
know, the real דאורייתא *de'oraita* is only סותר על מנת לבנות *soter
al menat livnot*. The real דאורייתא *de'oraita* is when you like knock
down a building because you're going to rebuild something in its place.
If you're just destroying it to get access to something and not
as a process of reconstruction,
that's מקלקל *mekalkel*. Okay, but it is interesting that the גמרא *Gemara*
started by completely redefining the case so it would not be a
סותר *soter* issue and then in the end when it got to
the seals on the manhole covers and whatever, it seemed to say
okay well according to רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* you're allowed to do
it to get to the food.
Without clearly clarifying—we could say מקלקל *mekalkel* and other explanations—but again the
גמרא *Gemara* did not really clarify according to that approach how it
resolves those issues.